A Guide to the Additional Louis J. Halle, Jr. Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10603-g
Additional Louis J. Halle, Jr. Papers 1938-1987
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10603-g
ca. 3,850
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Mr. Louis J. Halle, Jr. of Geneva, Switzerland, gave the Library this addition to his papers on July 1, 1987.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This addition to the Louis J. Halle, Jr. Collection, consisting of ca. 3,850 items (13 Hollinger boxes; ca. 4.5 linear feet), 1938-1987, contains a chronological correspondence file kept by Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s secretary during his tenure at the Graduate Institute of International Studies, Geneva, Switzerland, topical correspondence, and lecture notes, talks, speeches, articles, and book reviews by Louis J. Halle, Jr.. The composition of this group of papers is very similiar to previous Louis J. Halle, Jr. accessions but the collection contains more material from his tenure in the State Department, departmental correspondence as a professor at the Graduate Institute of International Studies, and many more of his earlier lectures.
The chronological correspondence file of outgoing Louis J. Halle, Jr. letters generally concerns the business of the Graduate Institute of International Studies, Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s lecture and speaking engagements, personal business, and the publication of Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s books, especially
Cold War as History
and
The Society of Man
.
Other topics include: the Cold War (November 8, 1965); the Foreign Service Act of 1946 (January 31, 1966); the Rockefeller Foundation(February 25, 1966); the division of Berlin in August of 1961 (March 7, 1966); response to George Kennan's comments concerning
Cold War as History
(April 27, 1966); Strategic Studies Program at Geneva(June 1967); notes on Peace on Earth Assembly at Geneva(June 2, 1967); problems with university publishing (April 21 & May 30, 1967); Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s departure from the State Department(April 11, 1967); Great Britain and nuclear weapons (April 11, 1967 & January 20, 1970); discussion of a curriculum of international relations (March 24, 1967); the development of East-West relations (March 3, 1967); contemporary history (August 3, 1967); violence and polemic license (May 13, June 12 & December 10, 1968); William Shakespeare's identity (February 5, 1968); the purpose of universities (December 19, 1969); the academic establishment (October 21, 1970); and Vietnam(June 26, 1970).
Occasionally miscellaneous articles and drafts appear in the chronological file. These include: "The Danger That Our Power Poses for Us" (ca. March 31, 1967); "Hamlet and the World" afterword (November 27, 1967); "The U.S. in the Far East" introduction (November 20, 1967); a draft concerning
Keesing's Contemporary Archives
(October 6, 1967); "A Multitude of Cold Wars" (March 4, 1968); " George Kennan and the Common Mind" (March 1, 1968); "International Behavior and the Prospects for Human Survival" (January 14, 1969); "Observations on the Proposed Program of Civilization and Foreign Affairs Put Forward by Fletcher" (June 16, 1969); "Professionalism and the Foreign Service" (January 14, 1969); colloquium on "Nato and Security in the Seventies" (October 8-11, 1969); "Between Arms Race, Arms Control, and Crisis Management -The Dialogue of the Superpowers" (September 15, 1969); "What Do We Mean By a World at Peace?" (March 6-8, 1970); and "Poetry and Statesmanship" (May 29, 1971).
Subjects or correspondents in individual topical files will be listed under the name of the file as follows:
British Broadcasting Corporation includes correspondence from George Fischer; the invasion of Czechoslovakia, liberalization of East Europe and the Soviet Union(August 28, 1968); a Dean Rusk interview concerning communism, the Vietnam War, Chinese-American relations, and the 1961 Vienna Summit Meeting between John F. Kennedy and Nikita Khruschev(December 14, 1976); a talk on the written English language and the theory of knowledge (August 24, 1977); and a talk on the human mind titled "Mind: Chance or Necessity" (July 29, 1977).
State Department Career contains several articles, "New Weapons and the Future," "History and the Present," "Our Deteriorating Latin American Relations," "The Problem of Formulating American Foreign Policy," "Communist Experience," "Force and Consent in International Affairs," "A Critique of Current U.S. Foreign Policy," and "Morals and Foreign Policy." Also present is a carbon of a letter from Louis J. Halle, Jr. to John Foster Dulles, July 28, 1954, written upon Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s departure from State Department service. In it, Louis J. Halle, Jr. urges the use of calculated restraint in international affairs, furnishing examples of problems resulting from lack of it and specifying objectives for the State Department.
Cass Canfield of Harper and Brothers usually concerns the publication of several Louis J. Halle, Jr. books,
Choice for Survival
,
Civilization and Foreign Policy
, and
Dream and Reality
, but also discusses the case of government atomic advisor Dr. Robert Oppenheimer(June 3, 1954).
Civilization and Foreign Policy contains reviews concerning the book, correspondence with Cass Canfield and Ivan von Auw, Jr., as well as George Kennan(January 26, 1955); Ken Thompson(January 3, 1955); Joseph Halle Schaffner(December 30, 1954); Dean Acheson(December 23, 1953 & March 5, May 26, & October 5, 1954); and Walter Lippmann(July 21, 1954). Also present is a biographical sketch of Louis J. Halle, Jr.(October 22, 1954).
Encounter includes several Louis J. Halle, Jr. articles and his correspondence with its editor Melvin J. Lasky. Among these are: "Truth and Consequences" (September 3, 1962); "The Problem of Two Germanies: A Fabian Approach" (February 21, 1964); "The Flickering Lamp" (August 13, 1967); "Lessons of the Nuclear Age" (July 4, 1967 & March 17, 1969); "Why the Revolt Against Hitler Was Ignored: A Note in the Margin of David Astor's Page" (July 8, 1969); " Karl Marx: His Death and Resurrection" (attached to October 7, 1969); "A World At Peace ?" (December 15, 1970); and "Western Cohesion and Alternative Patterns for the 1970's" (October 23, 1970). Other subjects or writers include: Alastair Buchan(July 4 & September 15,1967); United States student extremists (August 9, 1969); the "hero worship" of Mahatma Gandhi and Karl Marx(October 7, 1969); and the Japanese translation of
Cold War as History
(November 7, 1969).
International Institute for Strategic Studies contains Alastair Buchan's "The American Temper 1966," notes concerning the United States(June 14, 1966), and Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s "Strategy and Ideology" (September 13, 1968).
George Kennan's correspondence contains copies of many of his own articles, such as: "Credo of a Civil Servant" (February 12, 1954); Address at the University of Notre Dame(May 15,1953); Address at Princeton University(February 21, 1953); Address at the meeting of the Pennsylvania Bar Association(January 16, 1953); "History and Diplomacy as Viewed by a Diplomatist" (January 20 & May 1, 1956); "Industrial Society and Western Political Dialogue" (ca. 1959); and "Rebels Without a Program" (June 7, 1968).
Other topics include: Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s response to George Kennan's "Notes for Essays: 1951-1952" (June 19, 1953); the political slant of the security program of 1954 (December 15, 1954); morality in foreign policy (April 12, 1955 & January 9, 1956); Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s preparation of his lectures (March 8, 1957); Kennan's earlier tour of South America(March 17, 1959); the political environment of 1960 (February 22, 1960); Kennan's comments regarding
Cold War as History
(April 20, 1966); Kennan's
Memoirs
(January 16 & 22, 1968); Kennan's opinion concerning Richard Nixon's overture to China(attached to January 11, 1972); and nuclear weapons (July 17, 1977).
Manas has "Why is There No Voltaire" (July 31, 1968), and a discussion of the presumption of scientists regarding political questions (July 1, 1968).
Ernst Mayr concerning evolutionary theory (April 18 & 29, 1983) and his meeting with the young Louis J. Halle, Jr.(February 14, 1983).
Men and Nations folders contain scattered correspondence with Walter Lippmann and Alastair Buchan and several Harry Simple essays.
NATO Defense College folder consists of several lectures given by Louis J. Halle, Jr. at the College, including: "The Balance of Power as a Stabilizing Factor in International Relations" (November 9, 1976); "The Causes of the Conflict Between East and West (February 27, 1973 & September 10, 1974); "Basic Changes in International Relations in the 20th Century" (1973); "The Role of Military Force in the Nuclear Age" (1962); "Military Power as an Instrument of Policy in the Nuclear Age" (1958, 1959, & 1961); and "The Armed Forces as an Element of Power" (1958). There is also a letter from Stansfield Turner(July 22, 1975).
Nature of Power has a letter from Dean Acheson, October 26, 1954, and a discussion of the book title (September 28 & October 15, 1954).
Personal file kept by Louis J. Halle, Jr. while employed at the State Department and containing publishing suggestions, family correspondence, letters of introduction, and others. Topics and correspondents include: Charles Gamper(July 16, 1945); the protection of the Duck Hawk (June 18, 1945); Rita Halle Kleeman regarding community projects for Mexican laborers (July 19 & 26, 1945); Bolivian affairs (July 18 & 28, 1945); a Conservation Conference (March 30 & May 1, 1946); description of Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s various jobs in the State Department(October 28, November 3 & 20, 1947); article on birds of Argentina(October 20 & November 10, 1947); controversy regarding William Vogt's
Road to Survival
(January 10, 1949); and Andrew V. Corry(January 8, February 13, & April 30, 1949).
United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration mission to Latin America; Louis J. Halle, Jr. joined the organization as Diplomatic Advisor in August 1, 1944, and this file contains the itinerary for this wartime mission (October 9, 1944).
The third series of this collection consists of articles, books reviews, talks, and lectures prepared by Louis J. Halle, Jr.. The following publications represent the majority of these articles and book reviews:
Foreign Service Journal
,
Atlantic Naturalist
,
The New Republic
,
Encounter
,
Manas
,
Saturday Review
,
Audubon
, especially the issue on Antarctica(March 1973),
British Birds
, and the
Virginia Quarterly Review
. Among the miscellaneous articles is Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s letter to the editor of
The Times
concerning the Cuban Missile Crisis and the British Press (1962).
Louis J. Halle, Jr.'s lectures, 1947-1974, cover the period from his employment by the State Department until his retirement from the Graduate Institute of International Studies, Geneva, Switzerland.
Organization
The collection arrived at the Library in fair order and the orginal reverse chronological order and subject divisions have been maintained. The papers are arranged in the following series:
I) Chronological Correspondence (Boxes 1-2)
II) Topical Correspondence (Boxes 3-7)
III) Articles, Book Reviews, and Lectures (7-13)
Item Listing
- SERIES I: CHRONOLOGICAL CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence, 1969-1971; (5 folders) (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1968; (6 folders) (Box Box 2)
- SERIES II: TOPICAL CORRESPONDENCE
  - British Broadcasting Corporation, 1966-1978; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - State Department Career and Related Material, 1952-1980 (Box Box 3)
  - Cass Canfield, 1954-1966; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
  - Choice for Survival, 1963-1964 (Box Box 4)
  - Civilization and Foreign Policy, 1953-1956; (3 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Encounter, 1962-1973; (2 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - International Institute for Strategic Studies, 1962-1978 (Box Box 4)
  - George Kennan, 1953-1977; (2 folders) (Box Box 5)
  - Manas, 1967-1983 (Box Box 5)
  - Ernst Mayr, 1983 (Box Box 5)
  - Men and Nations, 1959-1962; (2 folders) (Box Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Articles, Book Reviews, & Speeches, 1953-1973; (2 folders) (Box Box 5)
  - Morgenthau Festscrift, 1975-1977 (Box Box 6)
  - NATO Defense College, 1958-1976; (2 folders) (Box Box 6)
  - The Nature of Power, 1954-1955 (Box Box 6)
  - Personal, 1944-1949; (2 folders) (Box Box 6)
  - Protection of Nature in Switzerland, 1970-1984 (Box Box 6)
  - Publishers, 1953-1973 (Box Box 6)
  - "Strategy vs Ideology", 1955-1956 (Box Box 7)
  - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration Mission, 1944 (Box Box 7)
  - The U.S. Acquires the Philippines, 1984-1986 (Box Box 7)
  - "Venice in Time", 1965-1977 (Box Box 7)
- SERIES III: ARTICLES, BOOK REVIEWS, & LECTURES
  - Articles in The Atlantic Naturalist, 1950-1975 (Box Box 7)
  - Articles in Foreign Service Journal, 1949-1969 (Box Box 7)
  - Articles - Miscellaneous, 1938-1985; (3 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - Articles re Nature, 1946-1987 (Box Box 8)
  - Articles in New Republic, 1957-1974, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - Book Reviews - Miscellaneous, 1941-1976, n.d (Box Box 8)
  - Book Reviews in The Saturday Review, 1941-1956 (Box Box 8)
  - "The United States in the Far East: Variations on a Theme", 1967 (Box Box 8)
  - Lectures at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, 1966 (Box Box 9)
  - Franco-American Conference, 1958 Mar-Apr (Box Box 9)
  - Lectures re the "Fundamental Character of International Relations" (Box Box 9)
  - Lectures at Geneva (Winter Semester), 1957-1958 (Box Box 9)
  - Lectures at Geneva (Summer Semester), 1958 (Box Box 9)
  - Geneva Meeting re "The Conditions for and the Character of a Sucessful East-West Negotiation", 1958 Mar 25-26 (Box Box 9)
  - Grimshaw Lectures, 1967 (Box Box 9)
  - Lectures on "The Historical Imagination", 1971; (2 folders) (Box Box 9)
  - Lectures on "History and International Relations", 1971-1972; (5 folders) (Box Box 10)
  - Lectures on "Ideology and International Relations", 1969-1970; (4 folders) (Box Box 11)
  - Lectures on "Ideology and International Relations" - Variants on the first six lectures, 1969 (Box Box 11)
  - Lectures on "The Korean War", 1966-1967 (Box Box 11)
  - Lectures and Speeches - Miscellaneous, 1947-19[74], n.d.; (5 folders) (Box Box 12)
  - Lecture re "The Object of and the Approaches to the Study of International Relations", 1971 & n.d. (Box Box 13)
  - Lectures on "The United States and the Far East", 1967-1968; (2 folders) (Box Box 13)
  - Lectures on "The United States and the Far East", 1968-1969; (3 folders) (Box Box 13)
  - "What Needs to Be Done in the Field of West European Studies," a paper prepared for the Ford Foundation, 1964 Aug 31 (Box Box 13)